Ivy Ledbetter Lee Papers, 1881-2003 (bulk 1915-1946): Finding Aid MC085
Public Policy Papers
- Series 2: International Affairs, 1923-1934; 2 boxes
  Material of interest in this series is the Miscellaneous Materials on Germany, including letters, notes and writings used by Lee to gain an understanding of the situation in Germany during the early 1930s. Material relating to the charges that Ivy Lee was under the employ of the Nazi government is in the McCormack Committee folder. The Russian Controversy file concerns the false accusation made in 1929 that Lee was under the employ of the Soviet government. Of interest are notes from an interview Lee conducted with Senator Mussolini of Italy in 1923, asking Mussolini what thoughts he would like to get across to the United States public concerning Italy.
  - Coolidge, Calvin Interview on International Affairs, 1927 March; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Europe, 1924-1933; 1 box
    - Communications from, 1928 January; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Cables to office from, 1931; 1933; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, 1924; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Germany, Miscellaneous Material on, 1931-1934; 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Dr. Gibbons, Herbert Adams - Interviews and Reports on Western Europe, 1927; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Gold Clause, Cables from Lee in London, 1933; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - International Affairs, Miscellaneous Notes, undated; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Keynes, John Maynard Memorandum, 1931 July; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - McCormack Committte, 1934; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Mussolini Interview, 1923; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Radek, Karl, interview with by Garret Jones, 1931 October; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Russian Controversy, miscellaneous, 1929; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Series 3: Travels, 1909-1934; 2 boxes
  This series will aid the researcher in establishing Ivy Lee's itinerary and the various people he met while traveling in Europe during the late 1920s and early 1930s. Also included are letters of introduction from a trip he made to Europe in 1909.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Letters of Introduction, Europe, 1909; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - European Trip, miscellaneous, 1928; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Austria, 1928; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Bulgaria, 1928; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Denmark, 1928; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - England, 1928; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Finland, 1928; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - France, 1928; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Germany, 1928; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Greece, 1928; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Hungary, 1928; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Norway, 1928; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Poland, 1928; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Romania, 1928; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Serbia, 1928; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Sweden, 1928; 1 folder (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Switzerland, 1928; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Turkey, 1928; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - European Trips, miscellaneous, 1929-1934; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Austria, 1932-1934; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - England, 1932-1934; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - France, 1932-1934; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Germany, 1932-1934; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Switzerland, 1932-1934; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, 1928-1933; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Series 4: Writings, 1907-1934; 5 boxes
  No arrangement action taken or arrangement information not recorded at the time of processing.
  This series documents Lee's writings: manuscripts, speeches, and manuscripts written under Lee's direction. The series provides some of the most comprehensive material documenting Ivy Lee's views, theories, and understanding of topics ranging from public relations, the railroads, and international affairs.
  - Subseries 4A: Manuscripts and Notes, 1907-1933; 3 boxes
    This subseries contains various manuscripts written by or for Lee. The materials in this subseries are almost entirely unpublished manuscripts. The volume "Notes on a Trip Over the Harriman Railroads," (the Union Pacific, the Southern Pacific, the Oregon Railroad, and the Oregon Shortline) documents in great detail Lee's activities and observances on the operations of these railroads. During his 40-day trip in 1907 he recommended various forms of publicity for the lines and described the general and economic conditions in the areas traversed. Other writings concerning railroads include lectures for a "Railway Transportation Class," the "Technique of Publicity," written for the Electric Railway Journal in 1917, and "What Ails the Railroads."
    The majority of Lee's writings concern the art of publicity. Lee explored the idea of publishing a series of lectures he gave May 14 and 15, 1924 at Harvard University under the title "The Meaning of Publicity." Also in this subseries is "Publicity: The Profession of Persuading the Public," a compilation of articles and speeches most likely written in the mid-1920s to educate the business leaders on the use of publicity. Other manuscripts on publicity include, "The Public Eye" (mid-1920s), and its revision "An Intelligent Citizen's Guide to Propaganda," which attempts to explain the sound and unsound aspects of propaganda. In 1928 Lee had his staff assist in the editing of another publicity book, "Mr. Lee's Publicity Book, 'an exposition of the methods and objects of publicity.'" The purpose of the manuscript was to show how public relations with its dissemination of information is important to the functioning of a democratic society. "Constructive Publicity," compiled most likely in the late 1920s is a collections of material on public relations and advertising. The last manuscript Lee prepared was "Problems of Propaganda: A Challenge to Democracy" in 1930. This volume is a series of addresses in which Lee "attempted rather to suggest enquiry...[in]to the problems which are raised in the present-day discussion of what are popularly and loosely termed 'publicity' or 'propaganda' activities." All the above manuscripts were never published.
    Lee also wrote on financial matters, particularly war reparations and their effect on the world economy. The "Gold Standard Memorandum" dictated September 28, 1930, reflects the view of some English leaders on the effects of the world-wide depression and gold distribution in the world market. "Gold Resumption in Great Britain," gives a very concise history of Great Britain's economic history from World War I to 1933 with the resumption of the Gold Standard.
    Also contained in this subseries is a manuscript written in 1930 that illustrates Lee's continuing interest in the Soviet Union. "Russia," is a series of information strung together on communism and many aspects of Russian social and political life from religion and women to the Comintern. The manuscript makes an attempt to synthesize much of the knowledge Lee had acquired and collected on the Soviet Union.
    - Public Relations Education Memorandum, undated; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Publicity, miscellaneous notes on, undated; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Publicity World War I, miscellaneous notes on, undated; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Railroad manuscripts, undated; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Russia, miscellaneous, undated; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Russian Revolution Notes, undated; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Trip over the Harriman Lines, 1907; 1 folder (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Pennsylvania Railroad, YMCA "Railway, Transportation Class" lecture notes, circa 1912; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - "The Technique of Publicity", 1917; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - "What Ails the Railroads", 1921; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - "What is Going On in Europe", circa 1922; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - "Building Prestige for a Store", 1924; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - "Meaning of Publicity", 1924; 1 box
      - Harvard lectures, 1924; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 6)
      - Harvard lectures staff memorandum, 1924 June; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 7)
      - final draft, 1924; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - "Publicity: The Profession of Persuading the Public", circa 1924-1926; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - "The Public Eye", circa 1924-1926; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - "An Intelligent Citizen's Guide to Propaganda", circa 1924-1926; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - "Mr. Lee's Publicity Book," material for, 1928; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - "Constructive Publicity", circa 1927-1929; 1 folder (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Gold Standard Article, 1930 September 28; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - "Problems of Propaganda: A Challenge to Democracy," compilations of propaganda addresses, 1930; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - "Russia", 1930; 2 folders (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
    - Gold Resumption in Great Britain, circa 1933; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous note on Publicity by others, undated; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Subseries 4B: Manuscripts for Lee by Others, 1926-1930; 1 box
    Lee on occasion would hire an individual or have his office staff prepare manuscripts from his notes on various topics because he did not have the time to do so on his own. "Capitalism" was written by Malcolm McComb for Lee and later revised by Lee. The manuscript offers a description of capitalism for the lay person. "Wall Street" was written by Frank Bellamy to illustrate who the leaders of Wall Street were and what Wall Street was like in the 1920s.
    - "Capitalism," written by Malcom McComb, undated; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - "The Probable Trend for Money Rates," written for Lee, 1930; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - "Wall Street," written by Frank Bellamy, 1926; 1 folder (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Subseries 4C: Speeches, 1910-1934; 3 boxes
    Ivy Lee's speeches encompass all the issues he was interested in throughout his life including economics, foreign relations, transportation, and public relations. He was well known for his capabilities as a speaker and was eager to express his views through speeches. Many of the speeches duplicate each other in part but the speeches are one of the best methods for researching Lee's thoughts, theories, and observations on all matters that interested him.
    The majority of the speeches from 1910 to 1924 relate to the "railroad question, situation, or problem," as Lee termed it. Generally this referred to the biggest single issue affecting the railroads at the time. For example, while Lee was executive assistant to the President of the Pennsylvania Railroad (1912 through 1915), many of the railroad speeches concern the campaign to raise freight rates. Most of the railroad speeches from 1917 to 1919 discuss government control of the railroads during the war.
    The November 1920 speeches and some early 1921 speeches offer Lee's recollections of conditions in Europe. Interspersed from 1921 to 1923 are also speeches on capitalism, personalities, the social order, the current situation in Europe, and publicity. All the 1924 speeches pertain to the railroad situation whereas the 1925 addresses only refer to public relations with the exception of a transcript of a debate between Lee and Charles Solomon titled "The Interests of Humanity can Best be Served Under Capitalism." In 1926 Lee spoke on all the subjects mentioned previously. Lee in 1927 and 1928 talked almost exclusively on Russia coinciding with the publication of U.S.S.R. A World Enigma, with the exception of a few speeches discussing publicity, and international relations. A majority of the speeches in 1929 discuss, "Protecting the Public from Propaganda." Most of the early 1930 speeches reflect Lee's interest in Asia having just returned from the meeting of the Institute for Pacific Relations in Kyoto, Japan. In the latter half of 1930 Lee's speeches turned toward public relations. The 1931 speeches document Lee's interest in the railroad situation and Russia. The 1932 speeches relate to war debts and reparations, newspapers and news makers, and publicity and advertising. The subjects of 1933 speeches are "The Outlook for the Railroads," "Use of Publicity in Sales Promotion," and "The Virtues and Defects of Capitalism." "The Contracts of Nations and A New Technique of Helpful International Propaganda" are the only speeches Ivy Lee delivered in 1934.
    - Speeches, 1910-1914; 2 folders (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
    - Speeches, 1915-1926; 9 folders (Box 9, Folder 1-9)
    - Speeches, 1926-1934; 10 folders (Box 10, Folder 1-10)
    - Speeches, undated; 1 folder (Box 10, Folder 11)
- Series 5: Personal, 1889-2003; 9 boxes
  This series includes a variety of material relating to Ivy Lee's personal life. The researcher will find information on Lee's immediate family. Lee would at times in his personal correspondence write on issues related to his professional life, and the researcher may want to look at the correspondence with Rev. James W. Lee, Cornelia Lee, and James W. Lee II.
  - Subseries 5A: Correspondence, 1896-1939; 4 boxes
    The bulk of the personal correspondence is with Reverend James W. Lee, Ivy Lee's father. At times they would correspond daily, and Lee discussed all major decisions with his father until Rev. Lee's death in October of 1919. Unfortunately, correspondence from 1913 through 1915, when Lee made some of the most important decisions of his life, is missing. The correspondence in 1917 and 1918 documents Lee's Red Cross work during World War I. Lee's mother Emma Eufaula Lee wrote about caring for Rev. Lee before his death and recorded observations on a trip she took around the world in 1927.
    During World War I, Ivy Lee wrote daily to Cornelia Lee, which provides a record of his day to day activities at the time.
    Correspondence between the children and their parents is also included here. Most of Alice Lee's correspondence is from trips overseas. Ivy Lee, Jr.'s correspondence is to his parents while in school or overseas. The correspondence of James W. Lee, II is of the most interest because he was in Germany from 1933 to 1934 to assess the German situation for Lee's work for I. G. Farben Industries. He was rather frank when writing to his mother about Nazi Germany, but he did not include much information on I. G. Farben. A letter of November 15, 1933 from Lee to James illustrates his thoughts on the work for I. G. Farben Industries. There is also correspondence from James on a trip he took to Chile as part of a delegation to commemorate the hundredth anniversary of the first shipment of Chilean Nitrate of Soda (an Ivy Lee & Associates account) to the United States.
    - James W. Lee, 1904-1919; 2 boxes
      - 1904, 1 folder (Box 11, Folder 1)
      - 1906-1912, 9 folders (Box 11, Folder 2-10)
      - 1916-1919, 4 folders (Box 12, Folder 1-4)
    - Emma Eufaula Lee, 1896-1928; 1 box
      - undated, 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - 1896, 1898, 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - 1919-1920, 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - from trip to Far East, 1924-1925; 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - 1927-1928, 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Cornelia Bigelow Lee, 1917-1939; 2 boxes
      - undated, 1 folder (Box 12, Folder 10)
      - 1917-1919, 3 folders (Box 12, Folder 11-13)
      - 1919, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - 1920, 1922, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 2)
      - 1930s, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Alice Lee (Cudlipp), 1914-1934; 1 box
      - undated, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - 1914, 1922-1934, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Ivy L. Lee, Jr., 1919-1934; 1 box
      - undated, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 6)
      - 1919-1934, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - James W. Lee, II, 1920-1935; 2 boxes
      - undated, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - 1920-1932, 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - around the world trip, 1929-1930; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - from Chile, 1930; 1 folder (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - from Germany, 1933; 2 folders (Box 13, Folder 12-13)
      - from Germany, 1934; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - postcards, 1933-1934; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 2)
      - 1935, 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous, incoming, 1896-1912; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous relatives, undated; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Charles Ledbetter (uncle), 1924-1928; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Lillian Ledbetter (cousin), 1926-1927; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Lewis H. Lee (brother), 1918; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 5B: Condolences, 1934-1935; 2 boxes
    These letters express sympathy to Cornelia Lee and her sons at the death of Ivy Lee in November of 1934. Included is a listing of all letters received.
    - Listings, 1934; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - letters, miscellaneous, 1934; 2 folders (Box 14, Folder 10-11)
    - letters from friends, 1934; 1 folder (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - letters from relatives, 1934; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - letters from young people, 1934-1935; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - letters from friends of Cornelia Bigelow Lee, 1934; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - letters to sons, 1934; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - resolution upon death, board of directors Waldorf-Astoria, 1934; 1 folder (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 5C: Diaries, 1893-1906; 2 boxes
    The diaries are generally concerned with day to day activities starting from the hour Lee arose. The diary from 1895 to 1898 gives the researcher a sense of what it was like for Lee to attend Emory University and Princeton University, especially his extra-curricular activities. The journal from Europe in 1905 was written expressly for Cornelia Lee. Included in it are memorabilia and descriptions of his travels.
    - Diary, circa 1893-1898; 3 folders (Box 15, Folder 6-8)
    - Diary, European Trip, 1905; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Diary, Panama Trip, 1906; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 5D: Manuscripts, 1930-1933; 2 boxes
    Ivy Lee's interest in Gothic cathedrals began during his first trip to Europe in 1905. He contracted with Orton Tewson in 1933 to begin compiling a book on Gothic architecture using Lee's many books and notes on the subject, but the project was never completed. In 1930 Lee attempted to create a memorabilia book with the aid of his office staff but the project was also never completed. The manuscript consists of a collection of clippings on Lee and his activities throughout his professional life.
    - Gothic Cathedrals notes, undated; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Gothic Cathedrals notes final version by Orton Tewson, 1933; 2 folders (Box 16, Folder 4-5)
    - Gothic Cathedrals correspondence with Orton Tewson, 1933; 1 folder (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - History, notes on, undated; 1 folder (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Memorabilia book notes, circa 1930; 3 folders (Box 17, Folder 2-4)
  - Subseries 5E: Biographical, 1923-2003; 1 box
    Lee was concerned with publicity for himself as much as for his clients. He had his office write up a number of biographical sketches on him and would reprint favorable articles on himself for interested individuals. Many of the biographies are rather short and repetitive. Included in this subseries is an interview with Ivy Lee, Jr. concerning his father and a masters thesis on Lee, Ivy Lee: Founder of the Public Relations Concept. The researcher may also want to consult various Princeton University senior theses on Lee, listed under "Related Material."
    - Biographers inquiries to family members, 1948-1989; 1 folder (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Biographies of Ivy Lee, miscellaneous, undated; 1 folder (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - "Emory Men Who Have Made History", 1937; 1 folder (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - "National Cyclopedia of American Biography" draft, 1939; 1 folder (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Office Biographies, 1923-1934; 1 folder (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Public Relations Society of America interview with Ivy Lee, Jr, 1970; 1 folder (Box 17, Folder 10)
    - "Ivy Lee: Founder of the Public Relations Concept" Stevenson, Howard G., masters thesis, 1949; 1 folder (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Ivy Lee Memorial Program, 2003; 1 folder (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 5F: Memorabilia, 1907-1985; 1 box
    Lee planned a trip with his family and a few friends across the country by rail in the summer of 1926, saving the itinerary and many news clippings of the trip collected over the journey. "The Trip Over the Harriman Lines" volume from 1907 contains letters of introduction, itineraries, and rail passes, along with various souvenirs collected during the journey.
    - Architectural Plans East 16th St. house, undated; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Book lists, 1935; 1938; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Bookplates, undated; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Client and Club membership lists, undated; 1923; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Coat of Arms, undated; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Funeral Service, 1934 November; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Insurance policies, undated; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Ivy Lee day, Cedartown GA, 1965 October; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Ivy Lee public relations award, 1985; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Leases and Mortgage, 22 Buckingham Rd, undated; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Passports, undated; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 11)
    - Seeing America, Lee family cross-country train trip, 1926; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Trip over the Harriman Lines, 1907; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Subseries 5G: Family Members, 1889-1935; 2 boxes
    This subseries contains material relating to Ivy Lee's immediate family. Alice Lee kept a diary of her trip to Egypt in 1926 for her family's benefit. She writes long descriptive passages on all she sees. Included are some letters of Cornelia Lee written when she was a child to her friend Grace Newton. Cornelia Lee saved information on her father's death in 1894, providing the researcher with information on the Bigelow family.
    Information related to Rev. James W. Lee consists of some miscellaneous correspondence with Ivy Lee's business partner George Parker and a manuscript Rev. Lee never completed titled "A Call to American Churches." The letters of condolence were written to Emma Eufaula Lee and Ivy Lee. Included in this folder are remarks made at Rev. Lee's funeral.
    James W. Lee II's materials give a first hand account of the first two years of Nazi Germany. James kept a diary while living in Berlin in which he recounts many of his daily activities, as well as various Nazi rallies and the notables who were present. The August 27, 1933 entry contains a long description of a Nazi rally in East Prussia. James Lee's memoranda and correspondence to the office in New York also discuss various aspects of the Nazi regime. The researcher may also want to consult the Visual Materials series for photographs taken by James while in Germany.
    The correspondence between James and Ivy, Jr. gives some insight into their relationship with other members of the staff while working at Ivy Lee & Associates. One of Ivy Lee, Jr.'s first responsibilities as a member of the firm Ivy Lee & Associates was to prepare a report on the 1933 World's Fair in Chicago.
    - Alice Lee, 1923-1931; 2 boxes
      - Diary on trip to Egypt, 1926-1927; 1 folder (Box 18, Folder 14)
      - memorandum, 1923; 1930-1931; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Cornelia Bigelow Lee, 1889-1911; 1 box
      - Correspondence, undated; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence to Grace Newson, 1889-1891; 1911; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Horace R. Bigelow's death, 1894; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Lee, James W., 1894-1919; 1 box
      - Correspondence miscellaneous, 1894-1919; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 5)
      - Correspondence with George F. Parker, 1904-1906; 1 folder (Box 19, Folder 6)